<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A glasse for the times: wherein is represented the malady and remedy of divisions. / In a sermon preached at Mercers Chappel, April the 7th 1650. By La. Seaman D.D. pastor at Alhallowes-Breadstreet. London.</title>
            <author>Seaman, Lazarus, d. 1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92775</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2175</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E597_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206295</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865469</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865469</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117710</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92775)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117710)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 92:E597[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A glasse for the times: wherein is represented the malady and remedy of divisions. / In a sermon preached at Mercers Chappel, April the 7th 1650. By La. Seaman D.D. pastor at Alhallowes-Breadstreet. London.</title>
                  <author>Seaman, Lazarus, d. 1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. and E.M. for John Rothwell at Sun and Fountain in Pauls church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117710:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A GLASSE FOR THE Times: Wherein is repreſented the MALA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DY and REMEDY OF Diviſions.</p>
            <p>In a SERMON Preached at <hi>Mercers Chappel,</hi> April the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1650.</p>
            <p>By LA. SEAMAN <hi>D. D.</hi> Paſtor at <hi>Alhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes-Breadſtreet.</hi> LONDON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ROM. 16. ver. 17.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now I beſeech you, brethren, mark them which cauſe Diviſions and offences contrary to the Doctrine which ye have learned and avoid them.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> and <hi>E. M.</hi> for <hi>John Rothwell</hi> at Sun and Fountain in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:117710:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117710:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable Thomas Foot, Lord MAjOR of the City of LONDON, With the reſt of the Court of Aldermen.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable and Right Worſhipful,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Trouble not my ſelfe with thinking what there was in my poor labours which might occaſion you, or any of you to deſire, <hi>that is,</hi> to command me to print what I had preached in your hearing. <hi>When we are weak, then we are ſtrong.</hi> May it pleaſe God to glorifie his power, through my infirmity; I ſhall rejoyce, and you ſhall reape ſome profit. But by this meanes I am forced to confeſſe (which otherwiſe had beene concealed,) that I had <hi>no Notes</hi> to bound my utterance then, or now to guide me in preparing for the Preſſe, ſave
<pb facs="tcp:117710:3"/>
thoſe which were ſince tranſcribed by a <hi>ready Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> without whoſe help I had not been able to let the world ſee what it was which you heard.</p>
            <p>My ſpare time ſince hath not ſufficed for to prune, and much leſſe to dreſſe and order the exuberancies, either of my owne expreſſions, or of his pen. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have I minded to file this little piece into ſuch a ſmoothneſſe of phraſe, or lick it into ſuch a comli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of proportion as might make it lovely and grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to peruſe. And though to inlarge the ſubject in ſome way of more particular, and quickning <hi>appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> might conduce moſt to the Converſion of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and Reconciliation among thoſe who through Diviſion are at enmity among themſelves, which was the ſcope of the whole; yet I am confined, to what you called for, and preſume not further, becauſe the ſlip is eaſie from <hi>a digreſſion,</hi> into <hi>a tranſgreſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray for the peace of your City, let them proſper who love it. And am.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, in the ſervice of Jeſus Chriſt, L A. SEAMAN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117710:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>MALACHI 4. verſ. 5, 6.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>5. <hi>Behold, I will ſend you</hi> Elijah <hi>the Prophet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the coming of the great and terrible day of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>6. <hi>And he ſhall turn the heart of the fathers to the children, and the heart of the children to their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, leſt I come and ſmite the earth with a curſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He words now read unto you, are the cloſe and <hi>Omega</hi> of all the Old Teſtament; A Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy they are, that's out of all contradiction; <note place="margin">Quod nos omnino non recipimus. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eron.</hi> Vide <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoph. Castrum.</hi> in cap. 1. <hi>Mal. Riberam. Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novium</hi> in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legom.</note> but whether it was delivered unto the Church of God <hi>in an extraordinary way</hi> by the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of an Angel, (as <hi>Origen</hi> and ſome of the Rabbies of the Jews conceive) or in a more ordinary manner by <hi>Ezra,</hi> (as many think) is not ſo clear, becauſe we have no Hiſtory con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Malachi,</hi> nor record of his parentage, neither in the beginning of this book, as uſes to be in others, or elſwhere.</p>
            <p>In the firſt of <hi>Mark</hi> and the ſecond verſe, there, <hi>chap.</hi> 3. <hi>verſe</hi> 2. of this ſame prophecy is cited, as a teſtimony of the Prophets concerning <hi>John, As it is written in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Behold, I ſend my Meſſenger before thy face, &amp;c.</hi> And by vertue thereof we may extricate and winde our ſelves out of that Labyrinth where the Jews or others would leave us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:117710:4"/>
But I intend not to be long or troubleſome in matter of Preface; I forbear alſo to ſpeak any thing of the Book in general, or the Chapter, (though it be but ſhort) becauſe the words are full in themſelves. In the Prophecy which they containe, two generall parts are to be obſerved.</p>
            <p>Firſt, here is <hi>a judgment</hi> threatned.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>a bleſſing</hi> promiſed.</p>
            <p>The judgment is threatned <hi>by way of implication.</hi> And the bleſſing promiſed <hi>in words at length,</hi> as we uſe to phraſe it.</p>
            <p>Concerning <hi>the Judgment,</hi> there are two things further to be taken notice of.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, <hi>the cauſe</hi> of this judgment which for name is here implyed onely, but from the thing expreſſed, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares to be Diviſion, or the diſtance that is betweene the hearts of the fathers and of their children, the fathers being againſt the children, and the children againſt their fathers; this is <hi>the ſin,</hi> the ſpeciall ſin that God ſeems here takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of.</p>
            <p>Then ſecondly, we are to conſider <hi>the nature</hi> of the judgment that is here threatned, and that is called <hi>a curſe; leſt I come and ſmite the earth with a curſe:</hi> It is a curſe and a curſe with a witneſſe (as we uſe to ſay) that is intended by the phraſe in Hebr. which holds out two ſeverall things. 1. Smiting, and 2. ſmiting with a curſe. That of ſmiting ſignifies alſo to kill and ſlay, and metaphorically to propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and diffuſe, all which ſenſes may not unfitly here be taken in together. As to ſmite with the peſtilence or ſword is to kill with them, and to kill abundantly, to poure out mens lives like water; ſo to ſmite with a curſe, is not bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſtrike or wound, but unto death and deſtruction, that many may fall into perdition, never to recover it.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Zachary</hi> 14. 11. you have the ſame word <hi>Cherem</hi> that is here uſed in the original, and rendred <hi>utter deſtruction; there</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117710:4"/>
               <hi>ſhall be no more utter deſtruction, but Ieruſalem ſhall be ſafely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited.</hi> Put both the tranſlations together and then <hi>the curſe of utter deſtruction</hi> is the judgment here ſpoken of. No leſſe the righteous Lord (as we may ſo ſay) had under his conſideration for to inflict for the ſin of <hi>diviſion,</hi> had not mercy intervened and found out way and means for the preventing of ſo great a judgment</p>
            <p>In <hi>Leviticus</hi> 27. (upon the peruſall of it) you ſhall finde a difference between <hi>the conſecration or dedication</hi> of a thing and the <hi>devoting</hi> of it. The conſecrating of a thing ſeems to be nothing elſe but a kind of conditional, limited and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ſetting apart to God with ſome kinde of caution and conſideration; and therefore things ſo conſecrated were liable to redemption or to exchange; Money might be given for them, and ſo the thing again for propriety might be taken away from divine uſe to be as a mans own for common uſe. But the things that were devoted, admitted of no redemption, nor exchange. Whatſoever was conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to God in that ſort, was ſo to remain and abide; And therefore this latter ſeems to be, (as I may call it) an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 28, 29.</note> dedication to God, the former a conditional. That which was ſo devoted to God, is alſo called <hi>cherem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Note this alſo, that things are devoted either <hi>by God</hi> or <hi>by men.</hi> By God, either in mercy or in judgment. If God do devote any perſon or place to deſtruction, thereby he makes it a <hi>cherem,</hi> &amp; conſequently it becomes irrevocably ſet apart to deſtruction, and there ſhall be no redemption, nor exchange, but that thing according to the appointment of God ſhall go unto that deſtruction to which he deſignes it. And thus all the reprobates in the world, and thoſe that are damned, they are all of them devoted, curſed in this ſence, becauſe they are ſet aſide by the juſt and unchangable purpoſe of God, to be veſſels of his wrath, that is to be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117710:5"/>
filled with wrath according to their deſerts. Such a kinde of curſe is meant here by this expreſſion, <hi>leſt I come and ſmite the earth with a curſe,</hi> h. e. leſt I come and devote it to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, leſt I bring utter deſtruction upon it, and there be no place neither for redemption nor for exchange; A hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie judgment, and that that may very well make our eares to tingle, and fill our hearts with horror when we ſeriouſly conſider that the ſin of Diviſion deſerves no leſſe a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>But thus briefly of thoſe particulars which pertaine to the firſt generall part, that is, the threatning implyed in theſe words.</p>
            <p>It remaines to conſider of the ſecond, that is, the bleſſing here promiſed. Touching that obſerve,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>the perſon</hi> promiſing. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>I will ſend</hi> Elijah <hi>the Prophet.</hi> The Lord himſelf is he that undertakes to beſtow this great mercy, who is <hi>Faithfull,</hi> therefore will certainly verifie his word; <hi>Omnipotent,</hi> and therefore able to performe all he undertakes; And <hi>exceeding gracious,</hi> and therefore as his power cannot faile him or us, ſo for his goodneſſe ſake he will not be wanting in thoſe things wherein he is ſo fully ingaged.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we are to conſider the <hi>thing promiſed;</hi> the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of all lies in this. I will ſend you <hi>Elijah</hi> the Prophet. Here we are to conſider the inſtrument God intends to make uſe of, and the work he appoints him to do, with the ſucceſſe thereof; for in theſe, joyntly conſidered, lies the bleſſing.</p>
            <p>The inſtrument is deſcribed in thoſe words of the fifth verſe, <hi>I will ſend you</hi> Elijah the Prophet. And the work he is to do, in the ſixth verſe; <hi>He ſhall turn the hearts of the fathers to the children, and the hearts of the children to the fathers.</hi> Concerning the inſtrument, you have him deſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Firſt of all <hi>by his name,</hi> he is called <hi>Elijah; I will ſend</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:117710:5"/>
               <hi>you</hi> Elijah. And ſecondly, <hi>by his Office,</hi> I will ſend you Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah <hi>the Prophet.</hi> And then thirdly, <hi>By the time</hi> when he ſhall come, I will ſend you <hi>Elijah</hi> the Prophet <hi>before the coming of the great and dreadfull day of the Lord.</hi> What is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by this ſame great and dreadful day, is not altogether clear amongſt all ſorts of Expoſitors; ſome referre it unto the firſt coming of Chriſt, and ſome referre it unto the ſecond. The ſound of the words at the firſt hearing, and the propriety of the expreſſions ſeem to incline very much, and to carry our minds to conceive that only the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond coming of Chriſt is intended. And thus the <hi>Papiſts</hi> for moſt part, becauſe it makes for their advantage in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther point, would have us to underſtand it. But if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well of all the circumſtances of this place, and that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation which the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> himſelf gives us elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, you ſhall finde that however the ſecond coming of Chriſt is not neceſſarily to be excluded, yet the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt muſt needs be primarily intended.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Malachi</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 2, 3. we finde the firſt coming of Chriſt ſpoken of without all peradventure: And yet concerning that firſt coming of Chriſt, we have there theſe expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; <hi>Who may abide the day of his coming? And who ſhall ſtand when he appears? for he is like a Refiners fire and Fullers ſope. And he ſhall ſit as a Refiner and purifier of ſilver, and he ſhall purifie the ſons of Levi, and purge them as gold and ſilver, that they may offer unto the Lord an offering in righteouſneſſe.</hi> There you ſee a coming of Chriſt which can hardly be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured by thoſe that ſerve in the houſe of God, which is yet but to prepare them for a way of more acceptable ſacrifice, and this muſt needs be underſtood of a firſt coming, for the ſecond coming puts an end to all kinde of ſervice, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according to the Ceremonial Law, but likewiſe accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Goſpel. And if this firſt coming of Chriſt is lookt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117710:6"/>
upon as ſo dreadfull and terrible a day, that the Prophet brings it in in a way of queſtion and admiration, <hi>Who ſhall abide the day of his coming? Who may stand when he appears?</hi> What ſhall we think of the ſecond?</p>
            <p>In the firſt coming of Chriſt, as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> tels us (who was this ſame <hi>Elijah</hi> here prophecied of) <hi>the axe was laid to the root of the tree,</hi> (ſo you have it in the third of <hi>Matthew v.</hi> 11.) <hi>And every tree that bringeth not forth good fruit, is hewen down and caſt into the fire.</hi> And when the Phariſees re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted to him; <hi>Oh generation of Vipers</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>who hath forewarned you to fly from the wrath to come?</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, had not you come and ſubmitted to this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Baptiſme, and made profeſſion of repentance of ſins, there was wrath of God at hand ready to ſeize upon you; therefore ſurely the firſt coming of Chriſt was a dreadfull day in regard of threatning at leaſt, though not for execution. The acceptable yeere of the Lord and day of vengeance of our God, go ſo together in relation to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall ſorts, Gods humble penitent people being on the one ſide, and the impenitent and unbeleeving people being on the other ſide, that it is no wonder we heare ſometimes of the mercy of his coming and ſometimes of the judgment. There is therefore no need why we ſhould underſtand theſe words reſtrictively and ſolely of the ſecond coming of Chriſt; for the nature of the phraſe and of the thing it ſelf will very well beare us out to underſtand it of his firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo; But the great thing which we are to eye in this ſame expreſſion, is, that before ſuch time as God comes in a way of judgment, he will offer termes of mercy; he will as much as wiſdome or mercy and juſtice tempered together do require, prevent his own judgment: There ſhall one come, a Prophet, a Meſſenger, a man of God which ſhall endeavour to win and gain the Jews to God, that the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117710:6"/>
of the day may not befall them; and this is that which makes exceedingly for the amplifying of Gods mercy in this promiſe.</p>
            <p>That however in juſtice he might ſurpriſe them una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, yet nevertheleſſe as he himſelf made it a law among his own people, That before they beſieged a place, they ſhould ſend offers and termes of peace; ſo he himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends <note place="margin">Deut. 20.</note> to do with them; they were to be mercifull to their enemies, and therefore he would not be wanting in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to them, to whom he alwayes profeſſed more then friendſhip. But on this particular I ſhall not ſtand any longer.</p>
            <p>The maine thing remaines yet to be conſidered of, and that is the work it ſelf, that this ſame Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to do. And here we are to conſider two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all the endeavour of <hi>John,</hi> and then</p>
            <p>Secondly, the ſucceſſe thereof. His paines and labour on the one hand, and Gods bleſſing which alone crowns all our endeavours.</p>
            <p>If we look not upon theſe two as accompanying one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, it is impoſſible that the curſe ſhould be prevented. If <hi>Iohn</hi> had altogether laboured in vaine, and ſpent his ſtrength for nought, the curſe would and muſt have come upon the Jewes; therefore theſe two things muſt be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of here to make up the intireneſſe of the bleſſing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, therefore <hi>Iohn</hi> ſhall labour the converſion of the Jewes to God, and their reconciliation one unto another: This is to <hi>turne the hearts of the fathers to their children, and the hearts of the children to their fathers;</hi> that is, he ſhall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly ſet himſelfe with all his skill and all his might, with all his parts, graces, powers and abilities, ſo far as in him lies, that he may in a faithfull diſcharge of his duty
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117710:7"/>
compaſſe ſo glorious an end as this is.</p>
            <p>And here beloved, conſider <hi>firſt</hi> of the ſubject which <hi>Iohn</hi> hath to work upon, and that is the hearts of men, a very hard task. They that have to do with mens perſons, the outward man, may happily win upon them and prevaile with them; but the heart ſeems to be of that ſecrecy and reſervedneſſe, and ſo impregnable to any humane power, that he that ſhall attempt any thing upon the heart of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſeemes to work in vaine: We have not the knowledge of mens hearts, and much leſſe power to work upon them, and yet this is the buſines <hi>Iohn</hi> ſhall ſet himſelf to in his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, to <hi>turne the hearts of the fathers to the children, and the hearts of the children to the fathers.</hi> True converſion lies in the change of the heart, and therefore <hi>Iohns</hi> labour ſhall be not to make men hypocrites and formall profeſſors, but true Iſraelites in whom there is no guile.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Iohn</hi> ſhall not onely have to do with the hearts of men, but with divided hearts, with hearts that are at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance one from another, that are alienated, and not eaſily reconciled; where there ſhall be a wonderfull diſorder and confuſion, the fathers being againſt their children, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren againſt their fathers; whether you take theſe words properly for diviſion in the family, or ſynechdochically, for diviſion of like nature in all kinds of ſocieties, as when inferiours are againſt ſuperiours, and ſuperiours againſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours; when Miniſters ſhall be divided againſt people, and people againſt Miniſters; and Magiſtrates againſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and ſubjects againſt Magiſtrates; in a time of ſuch confuſion <hi>Iohn</hi> ſhall then come in; and this is to be his work and buſineſſe to compoſe and reduce all into a right frame and order, that every one may act in his own Sphere, and performe the duty of his place both unto God, and in all other relations.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:117710:7"/>
Thirdly, obſerve the method of <hi>Iohns</hi> work; he ſhall begin firſt of all to bow the great ones, for ſo the words run, <hi>the heart of the fathers to the children, and then the hearts of the children to the fathers.</hi> He ſhall not apply himſelfe firſt of all to the inferiours, making them ſubmit themſelves to their ſuperiours; but ſhall firſt of all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at the top, at the uppermoſt end, at that part of the work that ſeems to have the greateſt difficulty in it. Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours may a great deal more eaſily be reconciled to their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, then ſuperiours that have authority in their hands can be prevailed with to be reconciled to their inferiours. It muſt be an over-ruling power that makes any reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in great ones; but herein ſhall be the glory of <hi>Johns</hi> miniſtry, that without any reſpect to inferiour or ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, he ſhall labour to bow and bend every one of them to the will of God, and turne the hearts of the fathers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the children, as well as the hearts of the children to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their parents, and <hi>ſoreſtore all things.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mas.</hi> 17. 11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Further, in the fourth place conſider the thing it ſelfe, that <hi>Iohn</hi> is to endeavour now upon this ſubject, when he hath to do with their hearts, and with theſe divided hearts, and with theſe hearts of fathers, as well as hearts of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; he is <hi>to turne them,</hi> to change, and alter them for to take away their diviſions and enmity, and to reconcile them, for to bring the hearts of all men in to God by true repentance and unfeigned converſion, and to knit and unite them one to another by love and friendſhip, an exceeding great enterprize; <hi>who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> as the Apoſtle in another caſe, and yet this is the buſineſſe that God intends to put <hi>Iohn</hi> upon.</p>
            <p>I, but what ſhall be the fruit of his labour? ſhall he have the honour for to be ſucceſſefull in ſuch an enterprize as this is?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:117710:8"/>
Yes, that's the great thing that God intends here by this ſame promiſe. <hi>He ſhall turne the hearts of the fathers, &amp;c.</hi> This is to be underſtood not only <hi>quoad conatum,</hi> as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his endeavour; but <hi>quoad effectum</hi> as touching the thing it ſelf, he ſhal do it, God ſhal uſe him as an inſtrument, and God ſhall bleſſe his miniſtry; ſuch grace and divine power ſhall accompany him in this kind that this work of the Lord ſhall proſper in his hand.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 16 where the <hi>Angel</hi> makes a Prophecy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand unto <hi>Zachary</hi> concerning his ſon <hi>Iohn,</hi> who was not then borne, we finde this among other things. <hi>Many of the children of Iſrael ſhall he turne to the Lord their God.</hi> God will grace him not only with honourable work, but with wonderfull ſucceſſe, however there be a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that ſhall not be converted by him, and it may be the farre greater part; yet many ſhall; what ever we heare before of the inſtrument, or of his work further then it hath this ſucceſſe, it wants of the fulneſſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortableneſſe of a bleſſing; for herein lies the compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it.</p>
            <p>Thus briefly of thoſe things that do belong to the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing promiſed, which was the ſecond generall part that I obſerved in theſe words.</p>
            <p>There are ſo many particulars here complicated toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as the proportion of time alotted for this exerciſe will not by any meanes ſuffice me to go through them; and therefore of thoſe many things that have been hinted at un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, there are only three that I ſhall endeavour to ſpeak farther unto.</p>
            <p>Firſt, of the ſin that is here implyed. And then</p>
            <p>Secondly, of the judgment that was intended for that ſin; and</p>
            <p>Thirdly, of the remedy of that judgment.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:117710:8"/>
Concerning the ſin that is here implyed, it hath no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect name in the words of the text; but a ſin is implyed, yea an exceeding great ſin; conſider two things about this.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The root and ſeat of it, it lies in the heart. And then</p>
            <p n="2">2. The fruit and conſequent of it. It expoſeth a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple unto a curſe, yea unto the greateſt curſe of all curſes. Two Obſervations here fall in by the way.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>1</label> Firſt of all, <hi>that God principally eyes the hearts of men,</hi> both concerning the good that is in them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the evill that is in them. If there be any good thing in the ſecrets of the ſoul, the Lord takes notice of it. On the other ſide if there be any wickedneſſe, any abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the heart, the Lord in a ſpeciall manner faſtens the eye of his obſervation upon that alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jeroboam</hi> was father of a wicked family, a ſon of Belial himſelfe, and a man that hath this brand laid upon him to all poſterity, <hi>he was he that made Iſrael to ſin;</hi> he could not be content to take his owne liberty, but he laboured to bring the people under his power to Idolatry. He made Iſrael to ſin partly <hi>by his example,</hi> partly <hi>by his command,</hi> and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>by his perſecution,</hi> by changing of their Religion he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volves all into ſin. Well, but now in the loynes of this wicked man there is one that God eſpies &amp; takes notice of, that had <hi>ſome good thing in him towards the Lord God of Iſrael,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 King. 14. 13.</note> the Lord takes notice of this, and it is not without record in Scripture. The words of <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> his wife you know; <hi>Whyhath Satan filled thy heart to lie to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 5. 3.</note> 
               <hi>the holy Ghoſt?</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, I do not ſo much take notice, nor God takes not ſo much notice of your words or of your faire pretences here, that you have (as you ſay) ſold all, and will lay all at the Apoſtles feet as belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers do to be diſpoſed of by them; there is ſomething elſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117710:9"/>
in your hearts. God that was able to give a power to one man to diſcerne what was in another mans heart, is much more able himſelfe to eſpie it out, <hi>Thou underſtandeſt my thought afarre off,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 139. 2. Look which way ſoever the inclinations of our ſpirits are working, the Lord fully apprehends them; <hi>all things are naked and open unto the eyes of him with whom we have to do,</hi> as it is in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4. 13.</p>
            <p>I will not be long upon this for the proving of it. It is a principle ingraffed in our minds even by nature, that God is the knower or the ſearcher of our hearts, and we take it for granted if we have any inward bent and working to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him he obſerves it, and therefore we ſuppoſe that a mental prayer ſufficeth to God, and that we need not uſe a voyce for information; if there were no other grounds for it in prayer, but that it ſhould be a means to bring ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to Gods knowledge that otherwiſe could not be, it needed not; God is the maker of the heart, and God is the ſearcher of the heart. But for the application of this.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> Howſoever Hypocriſie may be of ſome uſe and ſtead amongſt men, yet nevertheleſſe it can be of no uſe nor ſtead before God, ſave onely to make us the more inexcuſable and abominable in his ſight. It is prophecyed of Chriſt in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11. 3. <hi>He ſhall not judge according to the ſeeing of his eyes, nor reprove according to the hearing of his eares; But with righteouſnes he ſhall judge the poore, and reprove with equity for the meek of the earth,</hi> v. 4. <hi>And righteouſneſſe ſhall be the gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of his loynes, and faithfulneſſe the girdle of his reines,</hi> v. 5. Such a perſon God hath delegated to be the judge in all cauſes and overall perſons at the laſt day, and ſuch a Judge is he himſelfe; and therefore it is in vaine to pretend this or that, either in matters wherein we have to do one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117710:9"/>
or in things that do more immediately belong to the the Lord; for God ſearcheth the hearts, and he tryeth the reines; and therefore farre be it from any of us to pleaſe our ſelves in being Hypocrites; our firſt parents did vainly think to hide their nakedneſſe by a few fig-leaves; all our pretences are no better in his ſight, before whom all things are naked and open.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God doth principally obſerve the heart; let it be our maine care therefore to approve our hearts unto him. It is the great comfort of thoſe afflicted people of God we read of in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44. 18. that were under very ſore tryals, <hi>That their heart was not turned back from him, nor had their ſteps declined from his way.</hi> What ever we may ſuffer from God, notwithſtanding all afflictions or temptations which we may be exerciſed with, we muſt keep our hearts cloſe to him, in faith, love, feare and patience.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God is a principal obſerver of the heart; it will be our wiſdome therefore to give our ſelves and our hearts up into his hands, and not to truſt them in our owne keeping; let him have the ordering of them, and let us not leane to our own underſtanding. <hi>The heart is deceitfull above all things, and deſperately wicked, who can know it? But I the Lord ſearch the heart, I try the reines.</hi> Jer. 7. <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10. Therefore there is no truſting of our own hearts as they are in our cuſtody, though the duty of keeping the heart with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, be commended to us, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 4. 23. The Devill labours to get poſſeſſion of it, and to fill it; and we our ſelves are not able to withſtand him, eſpecially in his wiles and methods; And therefore as we commend our ſelves to Gods protection, ſo let it be our care to give up our hearts unto his holy Spirit. But I haſten to the ſecond ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:117710:10"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Diviſion of heart is a ſinne that doth exceedingly endanger a people.</hi> Look how much Diviſion there is in the hearts of men, ſo much ſin, and by that ſin they lye open to a curſe. This is an <hi>item</hi> moſt neceſſary for us to conſider of in theſe diſtracting times; we have long beene at enmity among our ſelves, and yet there is no reconciliation amongſt us, not ſo much as external from the teeth outwards; for in our words we know not how to expreſſe our ſelves as thoſe that are indeed agreed; but the Diviſion of our hearts is much more. However ſome men have ſo much wiſdome or pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy as to conceale their thoughts, yet notwithſtanding God takes notice of them; and when mens hearts are ſinfully divided, he takes it for ſuch a diſpoſition as is not to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured, but avenged.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Objection. </seg>
               </label> But may ſome ſay happily there may be cauſe, yea too much reaſon, that ſome men ſhould be of one minde and ſome of another; and conſequently when mens judgments differ, that their affections do differ alſo, is no wonder; and why ſhould it be counted matter of provocation to God? or why ſhall we feare in this reſpect more now then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> To this brethren I anſwer. Whatſoever the occaſion be, we ſhould compoſe our ſelves and our ſpirits to princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of love, they ſhould have the ſoveraignty in us at all times, whatſoever providence it pleaſeth God to exerciſe us withall; anger, zeale and hatred againſt the ſins of men, ſhould not tranſport us from the love of their perſons. But I ſhall ſhew you in ſome particulars a little more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly, when Diviſion imports more then ordinary dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When it eſtranges us from God himſelfe, to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like either of his Service, or Providence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When we are eſtranged in opinions and affections,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117710:10"/>
and thereby taken off from communion and duties of love one towards another. Diviſion amongſt men hath its ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal in Diviſion from God; for if we could keep our hearts cloſe to God by vertue of our union with him, we ſhould be the more compacted amongſt our ſelves, but when we begin a little to fall off from him, we are the more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and endleſly divided among our ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But will ſome ſay, I hope we fall not off from God in theſe times, we run not into idolatry and ſuperſtition, we make not voide the Commandments of God, by recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the traditions of men; however we are divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelves in ſome matters of opinion, and about civill things, yet we keep our <hi>firſt faith</hi> againſt Popery.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> But alas, then our hearts are divided from God when we are not united unto him according to the tenor of the firſt and great Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoule, and with all thy minde, and with all thy might.</hi> When a man hath a ſpirit in him that doth really obey God in the ſubſtance of this Commandment, then his heart indeed is cloſe to God; but if we be lovers of pleaſures more then lovers of God, as it's prophecyed of many in the later times, if we love our ſelves more then him, if we love our eſtates, lives and credit, or our relations more then him, we make them our gods. Suppoſe there be no groſſe idolatrous principle, we have no minde to worſhip the hoſt of heaven, nor to fall downe before any Image, this is a baſe kinde of idolatry, that we ſcorne; wondring at the folly of men that lived in former generations for things of this kinde; but the queſtion which we muſt put to our ſelves, is, whether we be not of a worldly minde, of that young mans temper, who being required to <hi>ſell all,</hi> upon a promiſe to receive <hi>treaſure in heaven, he went away ſorrowful becauſe he had great poſſeſſions.</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:117710:11"/>
And did you never heare that covetouſneſſe is Idolatry? It's much to be feared in theſe times, that many feare men more then God; this is a certaine ſigne that our hearts are divided from God; As alſo when we are exceeding ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous in thoſe things that concern our outward being here, but leave all things appertaining to the glory of God, to take care for themſelves.</p>
            <p>Secondly, hearts are divided when they are at a diſtance one from another. Ye know the ſecond Commandment, which is like unto the firſt, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe.</hi> And now there is nothing but ſelf love in us, when as one man takes no care for another, puts not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into another mans ſtead, but looks what power and authority he hath in his hands, this I can do, and this I will do, and this I may do, and this no body can or will trouble me in; this ſhewes our hearts are divided one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when we conſider not the caſe and ſtate one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo indeed and really to do as we would be dealt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; when we break thus with God and thus with men, this is Diviſion. Would you know how great a ſin this is? I beſeech you conſider of theſe two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, That when God would inflict a great ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual judgment upon a people, then he uſeth to make uſe of Diviſion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when God doth intend to bring a people un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to deſtruction, he prepares them for it by Diviſion. So as Diviſion is both <hi>the cauſe</hi> of judgment, &amp; <hi>the means</hi> to bring the judgment; and <hi>the ſigne</hi> and forerunner of ſome great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er judgment, and <hi>it ſelfe no ſmall judgment,</hi> as no ſmall ſin.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. <hi>v.</hi> 9. you ſhall finde <hi>David</hi> praying in this manner againſt his enemies. <hi>Deſtroy them (O Lord) and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide their tongues, for I have ſeene violence and ſtrife in the</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:117710:11"/>
               <hi>City.</hi> Violence and ſtrife are the ſins which ſtirred up the zeale of <hi>David.</hi> He knew that ſuch ſins expoſed people to deſtruction, and that Diviſion was the meanes which God uſed to effect it by. When God hath a minde to deſtroy, he needs not think of any other courſe then giving way to mens tongues. This he may moſt juſtly do to puniſh op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; for when men get power into their hands, they uſe it not for the intereſt of the perſons, with whoſe good they are intruſted, but for themſelves; this is a crying ſin.</p>
            <p>Holy men that are endowed with an extraordinary ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of diſcerning, ſometimes by way of imprecation call for ſuch a judgment as they foreſee God purpoſes to inflict, and then their prayers are not only prayers, but prophecies; and ſo it ſeems to be in the place forenamed. When God had a mind to deſtroy thoſe builders of <hi>Babel,</hi> he confounded their language, they could not underſtand one another; and ſo by that meanes, their enterprize had no other then a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous iſſue. In like manner when God intends deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to a people, he uſeth to prepare them for it by Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. It's worth our obſerving concerning the Jewes, they were many yeers contending about government from their coming out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> till their ſubduing by the Romans, whether the Prieſts ſhould govern them, or ſome other, till ſuch time as they were reconciled by a deſolation; God deſtroyed their Temple and their City, and by that means put an end to all their inteſtine quarrels about government. But till ſuch time as God had brought upon them that judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they could not be quiet; Diviſion ſo farre prevailed amongſt them, that when their City was beſieged by the Romans without, they had no ſooner gotten any little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite by beating back their aſſaults, but they fell preſently to fight as eagerly amongſt themſelves, as if they had had no enemy neere them. If we would know how likely a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117710:12"/>
are to be deſtroyed, or how near they are to a mercy, let us conſider with our ſelves how farre forth they are divid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or how farre forth they are in a way of reconciliation. The more Diviſion increaſeth, ſo much the nearer they are to ruine; the nearer reconciliation, ſo much the more hope of a mercy.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Hoſea</hi> 10. 2. the Lord obſerveth this, <hi>Their heart is divided, now ſhall they</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>be found faulty. He ſhall break downe their Altars, and ſpoile their Images; and they ſhall ſay we have no King, becauſe we feared not the Lord; what then ſhould a King do to us?</hi> The Originall of all miſery is this, their heart is divided, or as the words may be read, <hi>He hath divided their hearts,</hi> God hath brought this heavie judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on them, then they are a people prepared for deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>Now they ſhal be found faulty,</hi> that is, without any excuſe, nothing can be pleaded in their behalfe. <hi>A Kingdome divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt it ſelfe cannot ſtand,</hi> nay, it muſt not ſtand, becauſe it is not in a righteous ſtate.</p>
            <p>This ſhould cauſe every one of us to look exceeding ſadly and bleedingly within our ſpirits on theſe times, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our Diviſions; for in truth as long as this ſin takes place amongſt us, in that wonderfull manner that it doth, there can be no ſecurity; this heart-diviſion will upon all occaſions be a meanes to betray us; when our peace and happineſſe hath only an outſide foundation, that mens tongues are tyed, and their mouths are ſtopt, and it may be their hands are manacled, that they are not able to act as they would, yet as long as their hearts are divided, and there is an enmity there an inward broyling, and we grudge one againſt another, and bellow as Oxen do when they want fodder <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Jam 5. 9.</note>, and do but watch for an opportunity that we may be miſchievous one unto another, Oh beloved! can this conduce to the peace of the Nation; we muſt look upon
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117710:12"/>
our ſelves as in a miſerable condition while ſuch a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as this takes place amongſt us, to be divided from God, and divided one from another. This is <hi>the thing</hi> I would have you exceedingly affected with, this diviſion on the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers part towards the children, &amp; of the children towards the fathers; thoſe that govern cannot be reconciled to them that are under government; and thoſe that are under autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, cannot be reconciled to them that are in authority; Shall God reconcile us by bringing a common curſe upon us? Unleſſe he finde out ſome meanes of his infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to take away this ſin, we can expect no other but this very curſe that is here ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>But I would not altogether hold you in this ſad and dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full conſideration, either of the greatneſſe of the ſin, or of the danger of it; And therefore I haſten now in the later part, to ſpeak a word of the bleſſing promiſed; <hi>I will ſend you</hi> (ſaith the Lord) Elijah <hi>the Prophet before the great and dreadfull day of the Lord, and he ſhall turne the hearts of the fathers, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not trouble you with thoſe queſtions that belong unto the words, whether <hi>Elias</hi> be to be expected in perſon before the ſecond coming of Chriſt, or whether the words are to be underſtood onely of <hi>Elias</hi> figuratively, viz. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> according to the interpretation or application of our Saviour, becauſe the conſideration of theſe is nothing at all neceſſary to that which I intended in the choyce of the words. But there are two things I ſhall deſire you to obſerve out of them.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, <hi>when God intends to bleſſe a people, he will</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dectrine</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>provide ſome effectuall meanes for healing of their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions.</hi> Though he had a minde to ſhew mercy and do good to his people, yet untill ſuch time as he had prepared them for it by converſion to himſelf, and by reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117710:13"/>
amongſt themſelves, they were not fit for mercy; and therefore to make way for it, he here promiſes, <hi>I will ſend you</hi> Elijah <hi>to turne the hearts of the fathers, &amp;c. leſt I come and ſmite the earth with a curſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>the meanes which God principally intends to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctrine</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>make uſe of to heale diviſions by, is miniſtry;</hi> the miniſtry of the Word, ordinary or extraordinary, call it what you will, it is <hi>the meanes</hi> that God chooſeth to uſe for the healing of breaches, by <hi>turning the hearts of fathers to their children, and the hearts of the children to their fathers.</hi> To theſe two particulars I ſhall ſpeak a little further.</p>
            <p>1. When God intendeth mercy to a people, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a curſe, he will provide meanes for the healing of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions. The wiſdome of men ſufficeth not; all power and policy, all humane endeavours without him are indeed to no purpoſe; and the reaſon is, becauſe none of them reach the heart. Take the Magiſtrate that carries the <hi>civil ſword,</hi> go to the Generall of an Army that hath the <hi>long ſword;</hi> let theſe men try their power concerning the hearts of men, they ſhall be able to do nothing, becauſe neither the one ſword nor the other is a proper inſtrument to reach the heart or to work upon it; they can deſtroy the perſon, and take away the outward being, and ſo make a change in the externall ſtate or condition of men; but they are not able to make any inward converſion, nor to put a principle of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation into the hearts of men one towards another; the Lord reſerves this as his owne work, that he alone may have the glory of it. It is a work which he takes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, becauſe he alone is able to effect it; and therefore when we deſire or endeavour reconciliation one with another, our eye muſt be principally upon him, in whoſe hands are all mens hearts; the providing of inſtruments, and the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of their labours is his, and there can be no reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117710:13"/>
without him. It's a vaine thing therefore for men to endeavour reconciliation among themſelves, untill ſuch time as they have made a reconcliation with God; God is the party principall, not onely in the matter of offence, but in the buſineſſe of reconciliation; we offend againſt him, and therefore our great care muſt be to gaine him and to ſtrengthen our intereſt in him; when God is reconciled to a people, he will raiſe up fit inſtruments, ſhew them their work and their way, and make their labours effectuall. And although the inſtruments which he provides be unlikely, ſuch as promiſe but a very little, yet the work ſhall proſper in their hands; and why? becauſe God is reconciled, and provides meanes of reconciliation among men with a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to bleſſe Oh! how exceedingly are we beholding unto God, that he is pleaſed to take this great care in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving poore ſinners, that he makes it his work and buſineſſe to find out means of reconcilement; we are the parties inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that do the wrong, we ſhould take care to look after reconciliation; but the Lord diſdaines not to take this work upon himſelfe; it is no diſhonourable ſervice therefore for any man to put himſelfe upon it, to be an inſtrument of reconciliation; for God himſelfe delights to have the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this work, In 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 5. 19. we read <hi>God was in Chriſt reconciling the world unto himſelfe, not imputing unto them their ſins, and hath committed unto us the miniſtry of reconciliation; And we therefore as Embaſſadours in Chriſts ſtead beſeech you that you would be reconciled unto God.</hi> Oh the wonderfull love and goodneſſe that is contained in this peece of Scripture! God he begins the buſineſſe of reconciliation, he laid the plot, he found out the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument and the meanes, he contrived by his wiſdome this great myſtery, <hi>that the word ſhould be made fleſh,</hi> that his owne Son ſhould come and take upon him our nature,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117710:14"/>
and live in obedience to the Law, and yet ſuffer the curſe due to tranſgreſſours, and that we ſhould be freed from the curſe; and that this ſhould be made knowne to men by the miniſtry of the Goſpel, all this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is the pure deſigne of love. Well, therefore God muſt have all the glory of reconciliation; and all thoſe that deſire it, muſt in an eſpecial manner apply themſelves to him. Reconciliation can never be effected, unleſſe God be pleaſed; take God in and let him have his full intereſt, give we up our hearts to him ſincerely, and then the buſineſſe will ſucceed. But I haſten to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Obſervation, and that is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The miniſtry of the Word is a principall meanes that God pitcheth upon to make a reconciliation by.</hi> That we may the better underſtand this, I beſeech you conſider what there was in <hi>Johns</hi> miniſtry? (for our minds will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently be running thither) what ſingular thing that made it ſo effectuall for reconciliation and for converſion?</p>
            <p>I ſhall in a few Obſervations plainly ſet before you what is obvious out of the Scripture concerning the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt of all, <hi>John</hi> laid his foundation in ſelf-denyall, he laid himſelfe concerning his perſon as low as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly might be. <hi>His rayment is ſaid to be of Camels haire, and a leather girdle about his loynes, and his meat was Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth 3. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and wilde Honey.</hi> He came not, as our Saviour ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves of him, <hi>neither eating nor drinking.</hi> That is, he would not take to himſelfe the ordinary freedome that <note place="margin">Matth. 11. 18.</note> other perſons did; he was one of exceeding tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and abſtinence in all that belonged to his perſon; He was alſo very meane and humble, exceeding care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that no apprehenſions ſhould be had of him beyond thoſe that he was worthy of; And therefore when his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117710:14"/>
Diſciples envyed the dignity of Chriſt, and thought their Maſters honour would be eclipſed thereby, <hi>You your ſelves</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>beare me witneſſe, that I ſaid, I was not the Chriſt, but that I am ſent before him.—He muſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 3. 28. 30.</note> 
               <hi>increaſe, but I muſt decreaſe.</hi> Here was <hi>Johns</hi> principle and foundation; That's one thing that is to be obſerved.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in his miniſtry he eſpecially applyeth himſelf <note place="margin">Matth. 3. 2.</note> for the preſſing of repentance; that was the ſum and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of his miniſtry to call all ſorts of men to this duty, to convince them of the neceſſity of it, and that if they would have the forgiveneſſe of their ſins, and eſcape the wrath of God, they muſt needs repent, to declare both their repentance and faith, he required them to ſubmit to every ordinance that was of Gods commanding, and particularly to be Baptized; And <hi>to bring forth fruits meet for repentance.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 3. 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, he opened a dore of grace to all humble ſinners; for he told them of Jeſus Chriſt that was to come, and of the Kingdome of God that was at hand. <note place="margin">1 Joh. 1. 29.</note> 
               <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Lamb of God that taketh away the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 3. 11.</note> 
               <hi>ſinnes of the world. I baptize you with water,—but after me cometh one that ſhall baptize you with the holy Ghoſt and with fire.</hi> This is the third thing we have to obſerve in him.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, he did preſſe every one without reſpect of perſons, unto the duty of his place, calling, ſtate and condition. And therefore that <hi>Herod</hi> ſhould carry himſelf like <hi>Herod</hi> as a King, and that he ſhould take to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe no other liberty for ſin then other men; he told him to his face <hi>that it was not lawfull for him to take his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 14 4.</note> 
               <hi>brothers wife, &amp;c.</hi> And when the ſouldiers came before him, and put queſtions and caſes of conſcience, he preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <note place="margin">Luke 3. 14.</note> them ſtrictly to their duties, <hi>that they ſhould do vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:117710:15"/>
               <hi>to no man, neither accuſe any falſely, and be content with their wages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the fifth place, the miniſtry of <hi>John</hi> was rather <hi>practicall</hi> then <hi>polemicall;</hi> there were many diſputations in thoſe times amongſt the Phariſees and the Sadduces, and divers other Sects; but we never heard that <hi>John</hi> ingaged himſelfe in any of thoſe controverſies, but went on in the preaching of repentance and faith and obedience, not minding thoſe matters of leſſer difference wherein the Jews of thoſe times contended among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>But ſixthly, although the miniſtry of <hi>Iohn</hi> was practical rather then polemical, yet he was <hi>a faithfull witneſſe in the grand controverſie of the time concerning the matters of religion in that great queſtion, whether Ieſus Chriſt was the true Meſſias or no?</hi> And therein he alone bore up his head againſt all the <note place="margin">John 1. 8.</note> body of the Jews, and though he was not <hi>that light,</hi> yet he came to beare witneſſe of <hi>that light;</hi> In this he was ſo farre from not engaging himſelf, as that he became the principal, the hotteſt and moſt zealous man in this point, and upon all occaſions did labour to make it out in the moſt convincing manner, <hi>that Jeſus Chriſt was the true Meſſias.</hi> And when they would have had him to have thoughts of himſelf, as if he had been <hi>the man:</hi> When the Jews ſent Prieſts and Levites from <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to aske him who art thou? <hi>He confeſſed, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John 1. 19. 20.</note> 
               <hi>denied not, but confeſſed, I am not the Chriſt.</hi> So as though he medled not with leſſer things of difference, yet he conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the truth of this.</p>
            <p>And ſeventhly, there is one thing more I ſhall note to you concerning the miniſtry of <hi>Iohn, It was his great deſigne to prepare Diſciples for Chriſt, and to bring over all his Diſciples to be the Diſciples of Chriſt, and as much as in him lay to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie Ieſus Chriſt, and to vilifie himſelf, yea to make himſelf no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:117710:15"/>
               <hi>that Ieſus Chriſt might become all in all.</hi> In the third of <hi>Iohn</hi> there you have a very large ſtory for the confirmation of this. The Diſciples of <hi>Iohn</hi> take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of Jeſus <hi>that he baptized, and all men came to him;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John 3. 26.</note> they ſeeme to be offended at this, and thought that <hi>Iohn</hi> was wanting to his owne credit and reputation, if he did not ſomething to recover his dignity. Oh! ſaith <hi>Iohn,</hi> ye are my witneſſes that I ſaid I am not Chriſt, I am but the friend of the Bridegroome, and therefore I muſt be true to him; hereupon he ſtirs them up to beleeve that Jeſus Chriſt was the Sonne of God, <hi>And he that beleeveth on the Sonne of God</hi> (as he there teacheth) <hi>hath eternall life, and he that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Verſe 36.</note> 
               <hi>not the Son, ſhall not ſee life, but the wrath of God abideth on him.</hi> Thus you ſee that in <hi>Iohns</hi> miniſtry there was nothing of flattery, or complying with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny corrupt intereſt of the times; this was his plaine down-right way of preaching the neceſſity of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and of faith, and of a holy life; theſe were the great things to which <hi>Iohn</hi> applyed himſelfe, and above all, to drive on the intereſt of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; theſe are the characters of his miniſtry. Now ſuch a kinde of miniſtry as this is, the Lord delights to make uſe of to be the inſtrument and meanes both of converſion and of reconciliation, to turne the hearts of the fathers to the children, <hi>and the diſobedient to</hi> (or by) <hi>the wiſedome of the juſt, to make ready a people prepared for the Lord,</hi> Luke 1. 17. And now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved give me leave to cloſe this with two or three words of counſell and exhortation to you.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> Firſt of all take heed of thoſe men, and of that ſpirit which decryes the miniſtry of the word of God,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117710:16"/>
as if ſo be it were a needleſſe, vaine and ſuperfluous Ordinance, or as ſome pretend, no Ordinance, but pretended to be onely for the intereſt of ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons, and not for the good of mankinde, or common benefit of all ſorts within the Church. Certainly, this tendeth to nothing but more and more diviſion, to bring mens hearts farther off from God and from one another; its the Devils great deſigne, firſt to take men off from the miniſtry, then from Ordinances in general; when he hath prevailed with them ſo far, then alſo to take them off from the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, upon pretence that the immediate commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of the Spirit of God ſufficeth, and is all in all. But by this meanes he ſecures men to <hi>himſelfe,</hi> and brings them to be where he would have them, for then he is able to make his owne impreſſes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their ſpirits, transforming himſelfe into an angel of light, and cauſing ſomething in them that is not humane, but beyond the power of a naturall ſpirit; but thoſe elevations are no other then ſuch as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede from himſelfe the Prince of darknes, take we heed leſt we alſo be caught in his trap, as of late yeers many have been.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſeeing miniſtry is the inſtrumentall meanes that God pitcheth on to convert and reconcile by, let us pray that the Lord would be pleaſed to gift, qualifie and bleſſe the miniſtry of this age where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we live for ſuch a work as this is; for certainly nothing ſeemes to be more neceſſary for the glory of God, good of Chriſtians, then that ſome wayes of reconciliation ſhould be found out, and that the foundation ſhould be laid in converting mens hearts
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117710:16"/>
to God, thereby reconciling them one to another, which is not to be done without a reall change; it cannot be by outward power or by humane meanes alone, there muſt be ſome divine influence that muſt bring this to paſſe. God hath pitched upon an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and made that the way and rode which he choſeth to walk in. And however he ſteps ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a little out to fetch in ſome perſons, yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe he never uſeth to bauke this meanes, nor to decline this way. It hath pleaſed him all along, in all ages to carry on his great deſigne of changing the hearts of men by an Ordinance of ſpirituall efficacy, and not in the way of outward power.</p>
            <p>When God had that great buſineſſe to do to fetch his peope out of the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> however he could have forct them out of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> hands, yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe he choſe rather that it ſhould be done <hi>by way of divine oratory,</hi> and therefore ſends to him a Prophet; he pleads with <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and the Lord gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the miniſtry of <hi>Moſes,</hi> adding alſo a power of miracles and courſe of judgements till he made it ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall.</p>
            <p>But God ſets a ſpeciall obſervation upon this, <hi>That</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 12. 13.</note> 
               <hi>by a Prophet he brought Iſrael out of Egypt, and by a Prophet was he preſerved;</hi> Becauſe though Plagues and Judgments wrought moſt on <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> yet the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of <hi>Moſes</hi> as a Prophet prevailed moſt of all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his people. And when God had a minde to bring them out of the Babylonian captivity, and ſettle them againe in their owne Countrey, that was to be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected <hi>not by might nor by power, but by my Spirit ſaith</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Zach. 4 6.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:117710:17"/>
When God intendeth to reduce the later ages of the world by the deſtruction of Antichriſt, the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <note place="margin">Rev. 19. 15.</note> of the Jewes and the remaining Gentiles, the principall meanes to effect all this ſhall be the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, <hi>the Sword that commeth out of the mouth of the Lord.</hi> And therefore ſeeing this is the meanes that God in his revealed will hath pitched upon, we ſhould pray and encourage our ſelves in praying, that God would be pleaſed in mercy to provide ſuch a miniſtry for us, and give ſuch a ſpirit unto thoſe of this age and generation, that they may be inſtrumental hereunto.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, (and this all) Is the miniſtry, the meanes that God pitcheth upon for reconciliation? then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is not to be deſpiſed; the wiſedome or the judgement that God gives unto his ſervants the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Word, is not lightly to be ſleighted, neither may men promiſe unto themſelves ſecurely to contemne and ſcorne it; there may be more of the minde of God then we are aware of in the genius and diſpoſition of his ſervants; And therefore it ſhould reverently be reſpected; but eſpecially every one of us ſhould bow our ſelves to the Miniſtry, when it comes unto us in the power and evidence of the Word it ſelfe; my meaning is, Thoſe things that are clearly preached to us to be Gods revealed will, for ſinne to be repented of, errour diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced, order and government to be ſet up, when the miniſtry of the Word beates upon us convincing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in theſe particulars, we ſhould bow our ſelves, and look beſides the inſtrument that is ſpeaking to us, and conſider of the will of God, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſteth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117710:17"/>
it ſelfe hereby. Truely thoſe that are of a diſpoſition to ſleight the Miniſtry, are not onely ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much injurious to God, but wanting likewiſe to the good of their owne ſoules, as much as in them lies they labour to make that meanes ineffectuall, that God hath intended for the turning of themſelves and others, and likewiſe for the happy and comfortable converſe of men in this world.</p>
            <p>And here it muſt be remembred that more is not to be <note place="margin">Caution.</note> expected from the Miniſters of this later age then from thoſe of former time; we may not call for a ſpirit of infallibility, and ſay, unleſſe they be infallible, they be not worth the hearing. For, where hath God promiſed an infallible Miniſtry? and therefore why ſhould we tye him to ſend it? We are ſure of this, when Jeſus Chriſt aſcended up on high, he gave gifts unto men, <hi>Some Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers, for the perfecting of the Saints, for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 11, 12,</note> 
               <hi>the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt.</hi> If God had intended to binde himſelfe to give us Apoſtles, Evangeliſts and Prophets, we ſhould have had them, and heard of them for theſe 1600 yeeres that are paſt and by gone; but certainly they have beene nowhere to be found; and yet God hath not beene unfaithfull in making good his word, nor Ieſus Chriſt in taking care for his Church, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt ſuffice our ſelves with our Paſtours and Teachers. But we muſt look up to God for Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; whatſoever they are, they are but inſtruments in his hand, and farther then it pleaſeth God to bleſſe, they labour for nought, and ſpend their ſtrength in vaine. If we had Prophets and Apoſtles, if we had
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117710:18"/>
               <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> and <hi>Elijah</hi> in perſon; if we had Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe amongſt us, farther then it ſhall pleaſe God to bleſſe their miniſtry to converſion and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, they could not be effected by it; <hi>Paul may plant and Apollos water, but it is God onely who giveth the encreaſe.</hi> If God will vouchſafe encreaſe, though it be by the meaneſt of his ſervants, it ſufficeth; and if God with-hold, it is in vaine for us to cry out for other inſtruments. But I finde my ſelfe very much ſtraitned for time; thoſe things that have beene ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken I ſhall commend to God for a bleſſing.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:117710:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
